- So, Patrick, welcome.
So Patrick is the co
founder and CEO of Stripe.
He launched the startup or
now pretty big company in 2010 correct?
With his brother John.
- Well actually we started working on it
full time in 2010 but it actually,
to your comment just there
about companies launching,
it took us quite awhile to launch
'cause we had to get all
these banking partnerships
in place and so on and so we
didn't launch until September 2011.
And we'd been working
- Oh.
- on it for almost two years at that point
and every time we saw
PG or really anyone else
from YC all they would ask us
is why we had not launched yet.
(Interviewer laughing)
So some things don't change.
- That's interesting.
So two years until you had to--
- Yeah it was I think,
- practice.
- one year and 11 months from sort
of first line up code to public launch.
Which to be clear I don't recommend.
That is not a good idea.
Just we had to because we had to
kind of get all these
other things in place
and because it sort of too us
so long to have publicly launched,
versus, we tried to be very disciplined
about sort of gradually expanding
the number of users every month
and so even though we
weren't publicly available,
we got our first user,
like first production user
just kind of freelancing
and then every month
we tried to add at least
kind of a handful of users
and so by then we publicly launched
and we did have about
100 users which I mean
back then to us seems, that's a big deal.
That's very large.
- Speaking of, actually
when I was preparing
for this interview I was
trying to jog my memories
and I remember specifically because
your office was near here in Palo Alto
and I remember back then people would
always talk about the Collison
brothers running around
going to peoples offices and
like installing their API
into the web apps and in true
do things don't scale a fashion.
And I assume you were not only trying
to make sure they installed
it but also get user feedback.
And it happens so much that actually,
I don't know if you know Paul Graham, PG,
now calls it the Collison Installation.
(laughing)
And this is actually something we give,
we tell our founders to go do this.
Do the Collison Installation
'cause obviously,
in the hindsight it
seems so obvious to do.
- Well it sort of serves two purposes.
One is your point.
It serves as a really
good way to kinda get,
to use research and to get
kind of UX feedback and so on
and I mean if you've done this I'm sure
you had the experience where,
you design what you're absolutely certain
is the most streamlined user friendly
straight forward frictionless
way to do whatever it is
the product does and then you kind of,
you plant it and kind of
put in front of a user
and you just kind of ask
them to do whatever it is
and they find it completely impenetrable
and like they're clicking
all the wrong links
and they can't find the net button
even though the next button is
there blinking in green and such.
And so it's invariably
sort of incredibly painful.
There's sort of nothing so sobering
as watching somebody use kind of
the first version of some new product.
But the other reason for us was,
we had suggested to
somebody they use Stripe
of they switch to Stripe whatever
and invariably their response is oh yeah,
sure that sounds awesome but it can be,
they'll postpone it,
they'll postpone it again.
Just like there's never a moment
where it's like okay this is the evening
where I'm going to switch to Stripe.
And so us going and sort
of accosting them in
person sort of helped,
he'll talk in sales it's always like
a why you and a why this and why now?
And these kind of questions.
And going in person kind of
created a why now moment.
It's like well we're here at your house.
- Did you just show up or how did you?
Like what--
- I don't think we ever
actually just showed up.
Although, perhaps we should've but no.
We tried to be kind of
at least semi invited.
- Got it.
So Stripe now today, I mean you've come
a long way since back then.
I mean it's not even been,
it's probably been a decade.
Not even.
But I mean today you're,
well you have 1300 employees
across nine offices across the world.
You're doing, I have a list here.
You manage 200 million API requests a day.
You process billions a year for millions
of companies across 130 companies.
Your latest round of fundings,
Stripe is now worth 20 million dollars.
(laughs)
Billion (laughs).
Anyway the list keeps
going on but I'm not gonna,
I'll stop there otherwise people
are gonna think I'm your PR agent.
But anyway, you've clearly
done something right.
And so I want to spend a lot of,
I guess the time today talking
about running your startup
from the perspective of the
startup CEO, you yourself.
And it's kind of like zoom.
Like what do you think
about from zooming in
on the day to day
operations to zooming out
to long term strategic decisions?
So maybe to help us ease
into the discussion,
one thing is when you start off,
when from the very beginning a lot
of friends get together and they come
up with an idea and they're super excited
and they start working on it and then
at some point they need to decide,
ah we need a CEO for
this company (laughs).
And some people aren't meant to be CEO's,
but for you and John,
I've met both of you.
You're very smart, ambitious
people with great qualities
that and attributes that correlate
to becoming a great leader.
How did you and John decide
you would be the CEO?
- Well, I think Stripe is unusual for,
John and I are obviously brothers.
We've known each other
for a long time and,
(audience laughs)
and because of the relationship,
we're able to place a lot
of trust in each other and,
we really do run the company together.
There's no major decision that sort
of Stripe has made that's sort of,
that we've not both been a part of.
And it's not always the
case that despite being
the CEO that I'm the person who like,
in the case of disagreement it's
not always the case that I prevail.
Sort of our kind of dispute
resolution framework
is kinda much more around
which of us cares more?
Than kind of which one of us
holds kind of this title or that.
I mean John's title is President.
It's, those kind of sound,
both are significant roles.
And so, yeah in that regard
I think we're kind of an anomaly.
Sort of the fact that I became
CEO was honestly semi random.
And I know it, yeah.
I think because we're brothers being
able to kind of get to
this unusual situation
where we really do run it together.
- Great.
Is there a certain--
- Wait, sorry.
It may not be a helpful answer
because perhaps you're trying to encourage
all these companies like shit.
One of you guys has
got to be the CEO but--
- Well, do you think there's
like a rubric for this
of here are five questions
you should answer?
Maybe then you decide.
- That's a good question.
Hm.
- Maybe not.
- Yeah, I'm guessing it's quite,
okay well here,
I was on one thing which I think
it is important just to
have an efficient mechanism
for reaching a decision
and it can't be sort of,
simply orange around consensus right?
If there's sort of three co-founders
and sort of none of you
sort of quite want to,
or nobodies a clear CEO and you don't
have some kind of efficient mechanism
for sort of having decisions get made,
I think that is a recipe for failure.
And even I don't know, doing some kind
of quasi democratic voting is
probably not a great idea either.
And so for myself with John we kind of
both have areas we kind of
respectively specialize in,
and so that doesn't mean we
kind of have absolute autonomy
and authority there but we
kind of bias in that direction.
So he spends more time figuring out
and working externally with users,
I spend more of my time working
sort of internally on a lot
of product engineering things.
That's not to say that
he doesn't make decisions
there or I don't here but again,
there's a bias in that direction
and then secondly we have
this kind of additional aspect
where in the case of it
being a major decision,
and we sort of respectively disagree,
then we really do sort of
try to make it based on
sort of which of us is just kinda,
is more passionate about it and because
that will correlate with the outcome.
One of us really wants to do something,
or things that X or Y is
the right thing to do.
Simply sort of wanting it to
be so passionately is more,
I mean that can be kind of
a sort of self fulfilling prophecy
and so I think it's kind of not irrational
to have that be a consideration.
- Yeah.
And I also see like the best teams
that work well together are
the ones in which everyone,
they all want the best idea to win,
not their idea to win.
- Definitely.
- And so there's a stepping back
in an unselfish kind of way
to get to that conclusion.
- Definitely and I think that something
that we're kind of lucky
about that I think is very,
well exactly to your point.
I think it is definitely present in sort
of the most successful
co-founding relationships
that I have seen is some degree of sort
of dispassion and disagreement and,
for us I think that was
kind of easier to get to
because we had been disagreeing
with each other for 20 years and so it had
lost some of the emotional charge,
but I think that sort of
finding other mechanisms
where by you can get there such
that it's not sort of this, I don't know,
this kinda, the notion
of disagreeing strongly
is not sort of a scary phenomenon
that kinda of both parties
or multiple parties
if there are more than two are kind
of suppressing their feelings for fear
of there being this divergence.
- You have, how many more
siblings do you have?
Do you have more brother?
- One more sibling yes.
- Okay.
- Three of us in total.
- Would you guys, would
he join the (laughs),
or is it just you and John are the,
that's a special match there?
- Well he, the, Tommy my youngest sibling
he's sort of quite a bit younger
than myself and John and so,
- Oh.
- John is almost,
or is approximately two
years younger than I am.
And when we started Stripe I guess
I was about 21 and I think,
I guess therefore John was 19.
And Tommy was still kind of definitively
mid way through high school and so,
- Ah.
- just wasn't quite practical at the time.
- Yes, finish high school.
And now I think if you asked him
he'd probably say he'd never throw
his lot in with miscreants like us.
- Yeah (laughs).
Cool.
So in terms of the role of CEO,
often people say there's a
threshold in time in which,
and it's related to product market fit
where you have a role as a
pre-product market fit CEO
and then which is completely different
in your role as a
post-product market fit CEO.
So I wanna spend up most of our time
talking about pre-product market fit but,
just to collaborate those questions,
what in terms for Stripe what
was product market fit for you?
Like how did you define it?
Were there metrics to it?
What number of employees were
you at when you reached it?
So and so forth.
- Yeah that's a really good question.
And I think you're exactly right
to kind of divide things in to
sort of like there's kind of,
the story of a startup is two stories.
It's a story of getting
to product market fit
and then the story of kind of what happens
subsequently and
obviously there isn't like
a totally definitive
binary line between them
but I think it's kind of helpful
to frame the narrative in that regard.
I know it's good for Stripe,
and actually around the
time we launched publicly
I think is basically when we had it
in that when we launched
publicly in September 2011,
we had kind of rebuilt
significant components of Stripe
kinda multiple times in
response to user feedback.
Like we're kind of on the
third version of our dashboard
and the second or third depending
on how you count major version of our API
and so we'd kind of gone through
a lot of iteration response
to kind of the evident
challenges that users had
or the deficiencies the
product seemed to possess.
And when we launched,
we were basically
immediately bottle necked
on sort of being able to serve user demand
rather than generating user demand.
And I think sort of
directionally that's kind of the,
the sort of, the inversion that happens
for sort of in the early
days you're sort of
trying to figure out well okay,
kind of conditioned on or given some user,
how do I make sure that
it does what they need
and they end up a happy retained user
in a sufficient fraction
of cases or whatever.
And then kind of at some
point it flips for okay,
this sort of, well, I think
it's kind of very different.
Do you sort of take 100
users and some fraction
of them on board and some smaller fraction
that remain engaged or
whatever and so kind of
100 users that curve sort
of accentuates downwards.
And then you take 100 users and kind of,
again a meaningful fraction end up engage
and they actually tell
more people about it
or they sort of invite people and
I don't mean kind of strictly
just in a viral sense,
but just kind of generally speaking.
Just like kind of lead to and generate
more demand such as
things, you'd be sort of,
in some super linear
fashion kind of growing.
And I think when your sort of,
like being kind of less than one
is just very different to
being more than one (laughs).
And it sort of seems,
again when we launched,
I mean that didn't
generate that many users.
I mean I don't actually remember
but let's just pretend
that sort of 500 businesses
signed up on the day we launched,
but sort of immediately those sort of 500
businesses told other businesses
and people had heard
about it in all the rest.
So kind of, the next day we had a lot
of businesses as well and so forth.
Such that from the day we launched
the challenge became
keeping up with demand
rather than tweaking the product
to some how serve the market.
- When you launched how many
people were you at at that point please?
- We were about 10.
- 10, okay.
So, I guess before you launched then,
well your day to day
sounds like it was just,
like we were talking about earlier.
Just running around talking
with users and fixing issues.
Was that literally every
single day was it like that?
Or what were you doing everyday?
- Okay.
So not literally every single day
but I would say we really tried very hard
to sort of understand in
sort of very granular detail,
what exactly it was
that people were doing.
Where they were tripping up and so on.
So just to give you some examples,
we had a chat room for sort of
providing support when people
were integrating Stripe
and it was actually a public chat room
which kind of had some down sides
because if we'd broken something
or somebody had some kind
of embarrassing issues,
sort of everyone would see it.
We thought that was kind of good
because it would actually
kind of put more pressure
on us to sort of have the product be good.
And we had literally every time sort
for the first I don't know,
call it 10 users of Stripe,
every time somebody sent
an API request to Stripe,
like it sent an email to us.
So we were like looking at
every single API request (laughs).
And if we saw users do something weird
we'd be like well why
did they do that right?
Or kind of where were our
docs confusing or whatever
and so I'd go to dinner in
the evening or something and I've,
well again it seemed
like a lot at the time.
Id have maybe 10 emails because Stripe
was not handling a lot of the API
requests back then but sort of,
you're literally looking at
sort of each individual action.
And actually Stripe, we
just kind of celebrated
or at least in the passed,
we're not very good at
celebrating but we passed
our seven year anniversary
just a few days ago.
On September 29th and so I
was looking at our sort of,
we had an hourly stats
email that we used to send
and so on the day we launched we handled
sort of 22 payments in the previous hour
and which again sort of
seemed huge to us back then.
But I was noticing in that email,
I'd actually forgetting this
that we had things like,
in the email we literally had a list
of businesses that had submitted three
or five or something API requests
but it'd sort of not gone live.
They'd not launched their businesses.
We literally just had the
emails of all these businesses.
The idea was that we would then kind of,
we would literally individually
reach out to them as like hey,
you kind of seem to use Stripe
a little bit but you didn't,
you didn't go live.
Like did we screw up or was the prodcut
somehow inadequate or whatever?
We did things like every time anyone
ever hit an error of any sort,
that generated like a
high priority email to us.
And so we'd sort of try
to immediately go solve it
and that also kind of generated sort of
I think this pleasant
kind of user experience
where I mean it's frustrating when
you hit an error in some service.
But we could then often
sort of 15 minutes later
reach out to them and say hey,
we saw that you encountered this problem.
It's all fixed now.
And sometimes we did that even
in the case where sort of the
users made a silly mistake
and they'd kind of mistyped
an API parameter or something
and we'd just reach out
to them and be like hey,
noticed you had a typo in your code.
Which perhaps to some of them was
a little bit unsettling but,
at least kind of helped us increase
the kind of the throughput
product feedback.
But so, I mean these are all kind
of examples I'd say of the
sort of general pattern
of sort of really trying to be kind
of hyper attentive to
all of the micro details
of sort of how people
were doing the product
and kind of iterating
rapidly in response to it.
And generally speaking I think that sort
of pre-product market fit metrics
are actually relatively unhelpful.
I think you sort of,
you really want to bias
very strongly towards
kind of as much inspection
and kind of high throughput
qualitative feedback as possible
because probably not that many
people are using their product right?
And so, if it's 20 users you can kind of
in some sense afford to just like
look at everything they're doing
and try to understand kind of
what's working, what isn't?
- Yeah in some sense
it's how much do they,
you can tell subjectively like how much
they love your product
or how much are they
gonna probably be really
upset if it just disappears.
- Totally and actually
this point we had a thing
at the bottom of every webpage.
We had a little sort of text box
kind of anchorage to the
bottom of the sort of,
of the browser frame and sort of,
kind of one line high sort of text input.
But we had placeholder texts in it
to sort of try to prime people
to sort of try and tell us things.
And so it had, my favorite part of Stripe
is ellipses and people just
fill it out and can hit enter.
But we also of course had,
most of the problems were negative.
It was like the worst
thing about Stripe is
or the worst thing about this page is,
or I really hate the way
Stripe does or whatever
and again we would sort of,
sort of at that stage you
have to be kind of masochistic
and so again we'd be
sort of always waking up
to all these emails telling us
about all the terrible
things about Stripe.
But that was a sort of helpful
to do list for the day ahead.
- How did you stay happy if,
(audience laughs)
like in the early days I mean
before I reached the top it's
like I have all these complaints.
- What makes you think we did (laughs)?
(audience laughs)
So,
it was,
I would say it was,
well happy is such a
squishy concept right?
(audience laughs)
And 'cause like, there are
lots of things that we,
or I guess, when I look back and look,
maybe this is the
rationalization I taught myself
but when I look back
at sort of through life
at the things that I'm
sort of most glad I did,
I wasn't exactly happy while doing them.
Like often I was very stressed out
or I had to work really hard or whatever
but they're the things
that kind of post hoc
brought the most fulfillment.
And,
and I think that,
well I mean a part of it.
There's a rich literature here and
so I don't wanna kind of
dive too deeply into it
but I do think kind of
happiness is a tricky concept
to kind of pin down because is
it kind of happiness in the moment?
Is it sort of the sense that you have
a year later looking back and so on?
And so I think language is squishy
and it's not completely
specifically defined,
but I think kind of generally speaking
kind of a better utility function
and kind of gradient to try
to climb is that of fulfillment.
And so I would say kind of the experience
of doing Stripe was, it
was not especially happy
because we were sort of constantly sort of
incredibly aware of all the ways in which
the product was severely deficient
and all the challenges we faced
and I mean it seems sort of,
I mean there was no
Fin-Tack category back then.
It was just like two teenagers
or just over teenagers
trying to compete with PayPal which,
many people told us was not an especially
kind of promising avenue to pursue.
And so not especially happy per say
but it did feel kind of fulfilling.
Like I enjoyed working with John
and the kind of people we hired.
It was really fun
working with the kinds of
kinda customers we were serving,
they were just sort of business doing
all these kind of wonderful things
and they were kind of really smart people.
And it felt that like,
if it worked it could
be kind of consequential in the world.
And so I would say kind of,
it sort of felt like I mean, well,
I don't know what it feels like to be
sort of a scientist or something
but I'm guessing when
you're sort of pursuing all,
you have this kind of big question
and you're pursuing all
these kind of avenues
to sort of try to better understand it
and I'm guessing day to day it's sort
of not especially happy because
most of your experiments
don't work or whatever.
But sort of in, perhaps
there's some analog there
in terms of it still feels
in some sense meaningful.
- Yeah there, in some sense.
I mean day to day like you said,
you're just running around
with your head cut off,
but maybe on a weekly or
at least monthly basis
is just taking a step
back and seeing like,
what progress have I actually made?
'Cause week to week it's like 1% here,
1% here, it doesn't seem much
but from a monthly basis or,
maybe longer than that it
seems like there's movement.
- Yeah and I think
that's true and I think,
I don't want to, like I
think it's almost certainly
a bad idea to sort of work on a company
or to work on anything if you're like
truly unhappy working
at it right?
- Yes.
- And so there's kind of clearly
some balancing act there.
And I think, I mean a lot of,
well there's sort of so
many different sort of
difficult judgment calls
to try to make a startup
but of course part of it is like,
is something is making you unhappy
or if it just doesn't
seem like an especially
promising avenue or it's not
really working or whatever,
like your time has relatively
high opportunity costs.
Like you don't get to start that
many startups in your life right?
And so kind of knowing when to kind
of sort of call it quits
is I think actually,
I mean sort in startup dom we really extol
and to uphold the virtues and sort
of determination at all costs.
Never quit and so on.
And that's clearly not the right answer.
And like sometimes you should quit.
And so, so I think kind
of what you're getting at
is true and right or I
think there does need
to be sort of some happiness,
satisfaction fulfillment.
There's a good book of that name,
Satisfaction which I recommend.
Kind of week to week, month to month if
you're on the right trajectory.
- Oh man, I wish I had
known that I could've,
I remember when I was trying to,
when I was about to, but Stripe myself,
I had these bad memories of trying
to implement PayPal and
like stacks of documentation
and taking like five days
to figure it all out.
And so I sat down and like it's,
'cause you guys are saying
go it'd take you 10 minutes.
I was like no way.
And it probably took me actually
five minutes at that point,
and I was super happy.
I mean that's like, but,
maybe I should've sent you a review.
(Patrick laughs)
(Interviewer laughs)
- Yeah I mean that would've been great
especially if the review had
sort of criticism for us.
(Interviewer laughs)
- But no it was--
- It was really easy.
- It's definitely helpful
to have competitors
with not very good products.
- Yes (laughs).
Okay so, you were, in the early days
you were doing a lot of stuff yourself.
At some point, I guess two part question.
One is what were the things that
you weren't go do at and then two,
at what point did you hire someone to,
what I assume is to do those things?
- Well I mean, I'm not that
good at most things right?
And I say this in a non
sort of false modesty or,
I don't mean to be kind of
artificially self deprecating
but sort of for almost
anything that Stripe
has to do there are sort of people
who are better at that than I am.
And so I think to some
degree sort of the story of
say product market fit and to say kind of
our current stage is kind of,
implementing the recognition of that
in kind of more and more areas.
That said, I think maybe sort of embedded
in that question is okay well,
acknowledging that you're probably not,
that you're probably not the worlds expert
in any single thing it's
kind of in what order
do you sort of replace yourself?
And for Stripe the sort of,
the important thing we were sort of
most obviously not that great at
was kind of partnerships and sort of
working with the various
banks that we have
to sort of get on board and so on.
And so kind of we made,
in fact Jeff Ralston who
is here in the room today,
I think sort of was some combination
of sort of very supportive
and perhaps in the back of his mind
was sort of slightly pitying where
he saw us kind of trying
to get these partnerships
with these kind of big banks in place
and we really weren't sort of
getting anywhere very fast.
And so he told us that we had
to hire this guy Billy
Alveratto and I told just,
don't ask me questions.
Just hire this guy.
(audience laughs)
And at the time everyone
at Stripe was an engineer
and so we just we kinda
couldn't quite understand
what a non engineer would do.
(audience laughs)
Like if you're not writing
code what else is there?
And so we were kind of suspicious
or this idea and we sort
of we went back to Jeff
and we met Billy and he
seemed like a wonderful guy.
We really liked him but we
couldn't quite get past this,
okay but like but what does that actually,
how does this workout in practice?
And so Jeff told us that we
should hire Billy and if it didn't work,
or if the first few months or whatever,
then if it didn't work out Jeff
would sort of go back and pay his salary.
So it was this kind of
zero risk move for us.
And so, and we didn't
have a whole lot of money
at the time so that was not insignificant.
So, we hired Billy and that was sort
of an immediately
trajectory changing event
where previously when we'd gone
and talked to a bank I mean I don't know
if they're literally doing
this but it certainly
it felt they were kind of pushing
this security button under their desk.
Like why are these guys in my office?
(audience laughs)
And then suddenly things started to go
kind of much more smoothly.
And Billy is still with Stripe today
and has been an enormously
kind of pivotal presence.
And so that was, turned out
to be very helpful advice.
- That is interesting.
Jeff as an inflection point for Stripe.
Never knew.
Cool.
So it sounds like you had hired
actually people before Billy.
I guess your very first hire,
the third person between,
with you and John was an
engineer I'm assuming?
Like--
- Well he actually wasn't an engineer.
But he joined Stripe and he
started to become an engineer.
(laughs)
So, like he'd written a little bit
of code previously but he joined
and there was a lot of code
that had to be written.
It was a guy I know from college.
He's actually also Irish and,
yeah but we had a lot
of code to be written
and so he was the kind of person who
would sort of survey the landscape
and just do whatever it was,
was most important and required.
At that time it was writing code.
And so, off he went.
- So kind of the transition
from pre-product market fit
to post-product market fit,
a lot of CEO's when they think back,
this is like the one point in which
they think aw, I could've
done that better.
So, how did you grade your
success of that transition?
'Cause of a lot of it
is just taking stuff,
delegating stuff better and doing
other functions of the business.
So, what exactly was
your transition like and,
how would you, how could I
if I was going in your shoes
tell that I was doing it well?
- Yeah so I don't think
I did it especially well.
I mean I think kind of
fortunately sort of it worked out
but I think if I was
doing it all over again
I think we could've sort
of accelerated ourselves
by a year or two if we'd sort of
gone about it in a
somewhat more disciplined
and kind of self aware fashion.
I think the, I think one
of those kind of pernicious
sort of mental models you
can have here is the kind of,
you are on some growth curve and it is
sort of your job to sustain
or marginally inflect
upwards or kind of somehow,
you know that, what's that?
Is curling the sport where
you're kind of wiping the ice
while the whatever it is the
weight proceeds down the line?
Sorry I'm not Canadian but,
and but kind of somehow you're kind of
making kind of these
very small interventions
and perturbations on some kind
of underlying growth curve.
I think that's an easy
mental model to have
and I think it's kind of actively
kind of fallacious and mistaken.
I think that a much better mental model
to have is you're serving some market
and the market is I mean for,
it's relatively finite in size.
I mean you can always change the crutch
and increase the market size but sort of,
you can think of it as being finite.
And then there's sort of the percentage
of the market that you're serving.
And then whatever percentage
you are not serving
is kind of well you just
haven't built the sort of,
go to market functions and organization
that's kind of capable or at least
has yet sort of brought the product
to those market segments and they kind of,
the growth curve or adoption curve
is just kind of a function of
that go to market apparatus
but basically it's not some
kind of cosmic trajectory.
It's something kind of very much
of your creation and under your control.
And so what I, what we did
not do but wish we did,
is kind of maybe, well whatever.
Just after we launched we,
there's a whole bunch of kind
of immediate scaling work
we had to do but say
six months after launch,
we should've sort of mapped out the kind
of concentric circles of our market,
like maybe those kind of
very early stage startups
that were kind of our sort
of initial constituency.
Then those kind of all technical startups
but not necessarily very early stage
and then there was kind of, I don't know,
you keep going these kind
of success increments
until eventually you
get to say all companies
handling online payments
or something right?
And gone and sort of figured out
okay, kind of what's
the size of this market?
Sort of, kind of what fraction
are we currently serving?
What would it take to
serve more and so on?
And I think it's quite striking
you see that when kind of repeat founders
kind of go and start companies,
they almost invariably are willing
to kind of build the organization
post-product market fit.
So it's invariably willing to kind
of build the organization ahead
of where things are today.
Which I think is exactly
the right thing to do
because they're thinking okay,
I have the right product.
Now let's kind of work
backwards from okay,
what would the organization look like
that was serving the
entire market and let's
just start building that organization
because again the growth
curve is under my control.
And of course it's not like
100% under your control
but I think it's much
more under your control
then some people tend to think.
There's also of course a difference here,
a major difference when you,
I think you have sort of a consumer versus
kind of B2B use cases.
For consumer it's a bit more I mean,
people don't necessarily
know exactly what they want.
Once the market size for
like a news reading app
or a dating app or something.
I mean it's, it kind of, it
depends a lot on the products.
Like maybe way more people
should be reading news or something.
But for sort of a, some service or product
that sort of serves a discreet
logical concrete function,
that's sort of a set of
businesses or entities
definitely have or don't have I think
it's kind of much more rational
and much more mappable.
And I partly had this epiphany when,
Aaron Levie who's the CEO of Box,
John and I eventually,
we sort of had done Polo Alto.
We moved up to San Francisco.
I don't, well Aaron Levie
had Facebook messaged John
and we'd never heard of
him and we hadn't heard
of most people in Silicon Valley.
But he'd Facebook massaged
us like very early on
asking to invest in Stripe.
And I think John didn't know.
Who's this random guy?
And so we never replied and
but then we heard of Box
and we heard of Aaron and
we read his funny Tweets
and all the rest and so
we moved to San Francisco
and we invited him to our house warming.
I think it was the first
time we'd ever met him.
And sort of, like we're
not very good at partying
and so by sort of 11 p.m.
or midnight or something
kind of everyone was going home and,
but Aaron was still there and
Aaron stayed until like 2 a.m.
I sort of remember kind of sitting in
our front room telling us how much better
it was to be building B2B software
then consumer software for this reason.
Remember I said consumer software,
it's so hard to predict
sort of what people want,
they don't even know
themselves what they want.
You're kind of, you're, it's
such an amorphous space.
Whereas when you're selling
software to businesses,
businesses are kind of,
are mostly rational, are mostly,
I don't know what the
opposite of inscrutable is,
scrutable I guess and you can sort
of work backwards in a way that sort of,
it's just much more comprehensible
and so I still have this kind of,
it's like the angel and
demon on your shoulder.
I still have sort of 2
a.m. Aaron Levie sitting
on my shoulder sort of
extolling the virtues
of building software for entities
that know what they want.
- You've made the right choice.
Yeah in some sense there's
a lot less variables
or consumer there's a lot more variables
to consider and they're quite unknown.
Let's take a step back.
You talked a little bit
about thinking about,
thinking ahead about why your team is
or what your company
structure is gonna look like,
how do you, maybe this
is too big of a question
so maybe we can whittle
it down a little bit
but how do you think about that?
Like I'm sitting, if I'm
starting a startup today,
I'm close to maybe product
market fit but before that stage.
Like am I thinking about
this sort of thing?
Like what should my team look like?
What should my culture
be and stuff like that?
- I think that well, okay.
So, pre-product market fit,
I mean the goal is, really is just
to guess your product market fit.
And so I actually wouldn't bother thinking
too much about all these kind
of distribution mechanics questions.
Now you can get product market fit sort of
relatively quickly and so kind
of that pre-product market
fit stage might only last six months.
You're not necessarily like Stripe
where you're kind of in
it for various reasons
for several multiple years.
And so it may not last very long.
However, until that point I really think
you should just be thinking about okay,
how do I get there?
The main thing that I
think companies screw up
at the pre-product market fit stage
is sort of speed of iteration.
I think okay well, what determines?
Or you kind of speed of fruitful
iteration in that sort of,
I mean if you're kind of completely,
or if you're repeatedly
re-building your product
but sort of not in
response to user feedback
I mean that's kind of far less likely
to be kind of bringing you
in sort of a I don't know,
in a productive direction.
But if you have some kind of meaningful,
I'll be it perhaps smalls
of initial set of users
and you're rapidly iterating a response
to sort of their feedback
and sort of observed behavior
and so on then I think that's like
a really good spot to be in.
And I think again at that juncture
of pre-product market
fit it is kind of this,
you should be sort of doing everything
you can to tighten that
sort of feedback cycle.
There's a fighter pilot in,
or who kind of revolutionized
air born combat
in the U.S. in sort of the second half
of the 20th century the
Korean War and onwards
called Boyd and he had this
concept of the OODA loop
which was sort of, a sort of
a similar notion of the most,
in a previous, you go far you want to just
like the fastest aircraft or sort
of the most sophisticated
weaponry and so on.
Where he was all about sort of,
no you actually wanted to air craft
and sort of pilots in training that
are really oriented around sort of
the fastest sort of
responsiveness in iteration
to the kind of particulars
of the situation.
In a way that kind of subsequently went
on to to really inform sort
of modern aircraft design.
And so I think you wanna be like,
one of these sort of modern fighters
where you're sort of
really optimized to sort
of respond as quickly as possible to sort
of rapidly evolving situations.
Again in this kind of
pre-product market stage.
And so from a hiring standpoint I think
it should really be about okay well,
what's gonna sort of,
what's gonna get you there faster?
And I mean I think at an early
stage it's most likely well,
sort of just people who will help you
kind of build a product.
But of course not too many because,
I mean at some point, like,
being able to do more,
but you might actually be less responsive
'cause you're bigger team to
manager or something right?
And so as an empirical matter,
it seems that somewhere in between kind of
two and 10 depending on
exactly what you're building
is kind of the optimally responsive size.
But I think it really is about that
sort of time from observed
sort of necessity of deficiency
or this sort of characteristic
of your users behavior
to executed fix more improvement.
And for whatever it is that
kind of minimizes that.
- Is there, I mean you say two
to 10 which is helpful but is there,
are there observations
or evidence in which
you have hit the peak.
Like you should not add an extra,
like this extra person
- I see.
- is gonna be negative value
add to the whole operation.
- Yeah I mean every person,
every person, well,
startups in general involve
all these kind of impossibly difficult
sort of judgment calls and this kind of,
high dimensional possibilities phase
and so it'd be great if
you could sort of collapse
it down into a kind of a
friendly set of trade offs.
I just, I don't think you can.
However I think in principle,
calculations you're trying to run is okay,
each successful person takes time to hire.
And so slows us down in that regard.
Takes time to onboard, slows
us down in that regard,
kinda takes times to I don't know just
kind of meld with the sort of culture
and learn the stack, all that stuff.
That also takes cost and time.
Then involves subsequent ongoing costs
which is like coordination and alignment
and sort of, you sort of now have,
the organizations that distributed across
more neurons and so there's
that kind of persistent tax.
And that's not just
necessarily a linear cost
but it can be sort of
quadratic or something
kind of giving the multi
way communication problem.
So you have all these costs
to an additional person
and so the question is okay,
but this person can also help us
to like get more shit done right?
They can write more code
or talk to more users
or whatever and so it's kind of,
is that fixed benefit to sort
of that additional person
worth all these other costs and again
I think with the ultimate R biter being,
will we be more responsive to what
we're learning about our users
given the presence to
this additional person
and I think whether or not you will be
depends on the complexity of the product
and the complexity of the
market and all that stuff.
But I think that's in principle
the calculation you ought to be running.
- I've heard you say, and
speaking of hiring people,
I've heard you say the key qualities
that you look for in a future Stripe
employee is intellectually honest,
cares a great deal and just
loves getting things done.
Which are great attributes because
some people just don't
fit in those categories.
So, it's good to have
the separation there.
How do you, when you meet someone
how do you figure out
this is the right person?
(sighs)
- It's very hard and I wish I had
a more sort of definitive rubric.
And kind of particular set of questions.
Although if I had a
particular set of questions,
maybe they'd stop working because kind of,
people would learn how to
game them or something.
And so, I mean, well it's hard
to fake just being smart right?
And so that one's kind of
not as hard to discern.
And I, it's oddly hard to fake
being intellectually honest.
And sort of the characteristics of kind
of being able to see multiple sides
of a debate or an argument.
Like there are so many kind
of complicated questions
for sort of the only thing
that I'm really skeptical of
is kind of certainty in either direction.
Just 'cause the questions
are intrinsically sort of,
involve very contingent trade offs.
It's also, it's not
impossible but it's hard-ish
to fake just being nice.
Like something we hear
a lot about at Stripe
is just sort of people
who are pleasant and warm
and just sort of make others happier
as a result of their presence.
And if, well, perhaps if
you can fake that perfectly
forever maybe that's fine right?
(all laughing)
- Pretty much.
(audience laughs)
- But yeah.
They're all sort of actually,
there's no clear rubric for them
and I'm not sure
- Sure.
- that a clear rubric could even work.
- Yeah.
So, you talk about, like
get people who help move
the organization faster
if at all possible.
And I think there are two issues
usually that start slowing
down the organization
as you start scaling just 'cause
each person adds just more complexity
to the organization but also,
I think one is asymmetric information.
Just people don't want, like
are never on the same page.
And I think you've talked
a lot about this I think
and so everyone can Google around
for lectures you've given on this on,
you've done email transparency,
obviously having metrics transparent
to the whole organization.
But the second problem to that is,
if you fix that there's also
this asymmetric interpretation
problem which is,
everyone's there's this
like black box function
that how people interpretate,
even if all the inputs are the same
the outputs are all different and it's,
especially at your skill
now it's nearly impossible
to figure out everybody's function.
So, when you're thinking about creating
your organization and building it out,
like how do you reduce that?
Reduce that noise and try and
get everyone on the same page?
- Yeah,
well the first thing is
I wish we had actually,
between say five and 50 people,
I think we are much
too consensus oriented.
We of course weren't
completely consensus oriented.
I mean we couldn't have gotten
anything done if we were.
But I think we kind of biased
too much in that direction.
And again if I was doing all,
it's just not that efficient, right?
And sort of, it's
necessarily not the case.
And so kind of,
like you can sort of perhaps maintain
some kind of fiction for more or less time
but sort of ultimately speaking
there is no way of sort
of sustaining that.
And I think that's a relatively
common mistake right?
Because you almost invariably
come from some kind
of end musketeers for
sort of small and sort of,
kind of orientations where sort of,
there's no particular need for sort
of formal decision making mechanisms
or sort of subsequent communication
of said decisions or whatever right?
But then you kind of, you hit 15 people
and either is and I
think kind of companies
don't adjust quickly enough
to sort of that new necessity.
Again very much us included.
And so I actually think
we did relatively well
on the kind of ambient
availability of sort
of context and information and so on.
But actually kind of in some sense poorly
at sort of deliberate explicit
communication of decisions.
Decisions being I mean actual
kind of tactical decisions
or even bigger decision like what are
our priorities in the next six months
or things of that nature.
And so,
the hybrid piece of advice
and perhaps I'm over extrapolating
from our personal experience,
but the hybrid advice just kind
of reflecting back would be to kind of,
it's kind of like the pre and
post-product market fit thing.
But it's actually about the size
of the organization where it kind of,
if you hit a certain size and maybe,
I'm just gonna say 10 people
for the sake of simplicity,
maybe it's a bit before,
maybe it's a bit after,
I think you need to kind
of adjust more deliberately
to this kind of explicit
communication model of sort of,
of being sort of quite firmly
non consensus based and sort of,
I mean nobody likes the idea
of sort of being hierarchical.
That sounds pejorative but
like in some sense hierarchal.
- Sort of the top down,
like it does move things faster.
Maybe some people don't like that
but it does move faster.
- Yes.
That's right, that's right and there
is this kind of delicate
balancing act you wanna
sort of orchestrate where
kind of on the one hand,
you want to sort of
really prioritize speed
and agility which involves being kind
of somewhat hierarchical
because those are sort
of efficient sort of
symmetry breaking mechanisms
and ways to sort of to
have shots get called.
But on the other hand you really do
want people to have those kind
of strong ownership
mentality and real sense
that sort of they can
cause things to change
or identify problems or
sort of inject new ideas
even in unrelated areas.
And so it's this sort of delicate act
where I mean you definitely can
be excessively hierarchical.
But sort of how do you sort of facilitate
enough autonomy and agency but also
not have things devolve into this
kind of I don't know sort of,
uniform morass of sort of,
I don't know all these kind of,
of brownie and motion.
And I think that's hard and requires
all these kind of ongoing
sort of tweaks and nudges.
And I mean it's dependent on
the personalities involved
and all the rest and again I really wish
there was the kind of
the sort of row simple.
I'll just do X, Y and
Z and you'll be good.
But sort of if such X
Y's and Z's exist I'm,
no one's told me yet.
- If only there was a formula
for everything (laughs).
- If only.
- So riding on the same theme,
as Stripe grows, you
strike me as a company
that does the opposite of most companies
which as they get bigger
they just slow down
and they get less
innovative but for you guys
and it's hard to even keep up like,
you're just pumping out new products
and which seem to be successful to me
like Stripe Atlas, Stripe Press,
Stripe Terminal so on and so forth.
So, in the early days, when
there's just nine or 10 of you
if someone had a new idea
it's probably really easy
to get to you and then
you guys would decide.
How has that changed
over time to make sure
that someone who's like
six degrees away from you,
that a good idea actually gets to you?
And then how is that decision made
to actually execute upon it?
- Well I'm, it's very nice to hear you say
that you feel like we're getting faster
as we get bigger because we're constantly
sort of self flagellating over
how like frickin' slow we are
and like paranoid about
sort of, I don't know,
degenerating into I don't know,
some kind of I don't know
sort of immobile stupor.
And so to whatever extent
we do get things done
or appear fast I think
it's largely because we,
we're very paranoid in this dimension
and I think that kind
of the default outcome
of companies or course as they scale
is to become sort of more ossified
and rigid and sort of,
closed to new ideas and directions
and things that contradict
their prevailing
orthodoxies and all of that.
As to how we kind of avoid that,
I mean well, there's lots
of kind of obvious things
like partly it's sort of,
I mean having leaders who care about
the rate of progress and just love seeing
things happen quickly and
lots of things of that nature,
I think maybe sort od deeper rooted this,
we try to be a kind of
yes and culture in that,
I mean I personally love just ideas
and potential things we could do
and I mean most of them are,
I mean no matter how good the idea is,
sort of we should not
pursue most ideas right?
Even if independently it could be
a super successful company or something
but like there is a fairly finite number
of things we can do and so sort of,
you kind of on the one hand need
to recognize that intellectually
and just like not pursue most things.
On the other hand enjoying the exercise
and contemplating well, what would it
look like if we did it right?
And so one thing we do
every year for example
is we have this kind of crazy
ideas process we call it
where we literally send a
document to the whole company,
a hack pod document
that's open to everyone
and people can sort of add ideas to it,
they think are probably a bad idea
but if they worked might be a great idea.
And it's very important that they
have to be probably a bad idea
because if they're like
probably a good idea
then I mean it's not that risky
and I mean kind of by definition we
should probably do it and so whatever.
Maybe we should just do it.
And so, people like really self sensor
a lot in most organizations because
they don't want to look stupid and
they don't want to be sort of associated
with just having all
these like wacky bad ideas
and so on and so we try to be fairly firm
that if you add ideas to this
it has to be probably a bad idea.
And actually a lot of cool things
we've subsequently gone on and done
first came from that process.
Stripe App was being one of them.
And also we sort of helped
Stellar get off the ground,
this sort of cryptic
currency back a few years ago
and sort of that also sort
of came from this process.
And so that's one of the mechanisms
by which we try to have that
kind of yes and culture.
And I really think there aren't that many,
as just as an empirical matter,
there aren't that many large organizations
that I think sort of really
do this successfully.
But I think that sort of the
most successful larger organizations
somehow do succeed in
sort of this iterative
repeated process of kind of augmentation.
Amazon and Google being kind
of the most prominent examples.
Where obviously when Google launched
there was no Gmail or YouTube or Android
or Google Maps or whatever.
And Amazon sort of is kind of
an even more conspicuous
example in some sense
of this kind of repeated attach
at successful ancillary businesses.
And so I think kind of,
yeah it's a very natural
temptation as you grow
to I think becoming
increasingly close to this.
I think it's very important to avoid.
- Cool.
So I have a couple more questions
and then maybe we'll have time
to take questions from the audience.
One is, looking back, is there something,
did you have a strong opinion of
how startups should be run as a CEO
that have just completely reversed
because you're now the CEO?
(audience member coughing)
- That's a good question.
- Another way to potentially put it
is like what are things that you did
where you're like I know for
sure this should've been done
and then it just turned out
to be a mistake (laughs)?
- Right.
Well I already mentioned the sort of,
the consensus orientation.
One that we're going through right now
which is a quite sort of
significant divergence
is we were sort of fairly centralized
up until sort of relatively recently.
I mean we had some remote employees
from a pretty early stage
but by and large Stripe
was kinda concentrated in San Francisco.
Last week we announced
our fourth global hub
and basically what we've decided to do
is we're gonna have kind of major sort
of project and engineering sort of efforts
and teams and functions and
all the rest in San Francisco,
also in Seattle, also in
Dublin and also in Singapore.
And so these non San Francisco locations
are not gonna be sort of I don't know,
operations offices or satellite offices
or places where we do some kind
of localization and
local market adaptation.
We want to have kind of
completely de novo new products
that sort of become super successful
started out of these offices.
And that's not the sort
of centered obviously
kind of Silicon Valley pattern
versus Apple and Amazon and Facebook
and Google and all these companies tend
to be sort of highly concentrated in these
sort of very sort of monolithic
corporate headquarters.
And our thesis is that
it's kind of several folds.
Partly that kind of the
availability of talent
is becoming sort of far more
geographically dispersed.
Partly that sort of the Bay
area's becoming increasing
untenable expensive location to locate.
And partly that sort of,
we really want Stripe
to be global infrastructure that works
kind of just as well in
sort of Asian markets
or in Latin American markets or whatever
as it does for businesses in the U.S.
and kind of the era of the internet being
a predominately North American
or North American Western
European or whatever,
the days of being kind of
such a phenomenon are over.
And so, I think that's sort
of a fairly substantial break
with kind of descriptive
best practice of the past.
I mean we obviously think it'll work.
I mean we wouldn't do it if we didn't
but it is also kind of
on some level risky.
Like we don't have good
prior examples to point to
and I mean there's some great companies
in Singapore like Grab and Carousel.
There aren't really
sort of any examples yet
of sort of American companies establishing
kind of major private
engineering hubs there.
We're pretty optimistic it can be done
but if it works we'll be the
first or one of the first.
- Cool.
Last question.
So in 100 years from now
what is Stripe gonna be?
What do you imagine it to be?
- Well we're only seven
years old so that's a,
(audience laughs)
a full question to answer.
I mean we're trying to build this kind of,
this economic infrastructure
for the internet
and this sort of platform
for globalization
and kind of I don't know,
sort of technological progress
in the sense that like it
ought to be just as easy
to start a company in sort of Nigeria
as it is New York and it should be
just as easy for somebody in Brazil
to buy something sort of from any
of these companies as it is for again
somebody in the Western world.
And,
it just just seemed so crazy to me
that sort of that hasn't happened yet.
Like I, it sort of feels Stripe
should've happened 10 or 20 years
before it did and kind of,
I don't so much think that we're sort of
pursuing this sort of unprecedented
kind of path breaking or,
sort of inconceivable idea so much
as kind of correcting a deficiency
in sort of a rip in the fabric
of internet infrastructure.
And so anyway I think we still have
at least five years to go in sort
of correcting this inadequacy.
As to what happens
after that I'm not sure.
- Got it.
In some sense in the
future all transactions
should be digital and they could very well
just all be going through Stripe.
I mean right now like, in the U.S. someone
was telling me like 80% of all Americans
have done some transaction
through Stripe right?
- Yeah that's right.
So in the last 12 months, more
than 80% of American adults
have bought something
from a Stripe business.
At least one thing from a Stripe business.
Which is cool and it's not
just the case in the U.S.
Like in Singapore where I was last week,
that figure is about 70% right?
But I guess we don't think about,
well I think about it more in terms of
the things that are possible
or get started as in it's kind of,
we think a lot about the rate
of sort of new firm creation.
What companies are getting started,
how successful are those companies?
Which markets can they serve and so on
and every now and again we look back
and we look at sort of those
kinds of market coverage stats.
But I guess that's not
really what sort of,
what motivates it.
It's more that sort of
there are these businesses
that should exist and or should
be able to offer their
products and services
in these place where they currently can't
and that's I think, I
mean, that's the kind
of thinking that we use to kind
of inform the product and that sort of
is kind of the core I don't know,
locomotion day to day and then maybe
the outcome of that is that I don't know,
all these people get to that info from it.
- Alright.
Thank you so much Patrick.
- Cool, thank you.
- This was great.
(audience applauding)